so we're discussing the other day about
the middle way it was between
asceticism you know the two extremes
but the middle way is the
enduring of thoughts
uh yes yes that's certainly the way to
cultivate the middle way where to
cultivate that
because the sensuality like from the
context of thoughts from the point of
view of thoughts and mental images that
appear in people's minds
sensuality would be acting out of
thoughts immediately so you have a thought
immediately so you have a thought
towards something
you just act out of it there is no
reflection there is no sense restraint
there is no consideration
more or less so to that that kind of
that's pretty much what defines
uh centrality and as the buddha said
it's the
it's the man's thought lust and desiring
his thoughts
that makes his centrality be there it's
not the beautiful things in the world
so the nature of thought is central
thought but it's also it's paired with
that just immediate acceptance of it
just immediate acceptance of it
immediate delight in it immediate
welcoming of it
which means immediate acting towards
whatever you're thinking of
and the opposite way would be like say
you see sexuality as a problem
so what do you do then well you try to
deny the thoughts
so you see that yes when these thoughts
of central desires arise in me
i act out of it so what if i were to not
have those thoughts
and then you want to prevent them from
arising and that's now
more aligned with that self self
modification the ignoble way of
of just self torture because it can it
cannot bear the result you want
that's why it's ignorable that's why it
does not it's not wholesome
not that trying to resist thoughts is
bad but
see denying thoughts requires you to
resist thoughts but it takes it even
further now it overshoots
in the other way because one thing is
you're resisting the thoughts
means exactly that allowing them to
endure but resisting you acting out of
it
and another thing is now to oh i mustn't
have these thoughts to begin with
now that's you overreaching that's not
up to you
and that's why either giving into those
thoughts or trying to deny them
you're equally ignorant you're either
bound with sexuality or
self-modification you're bound with the
same domain
of bait as the buddha described bait
that matter lays down for you
so how do you then not go into either of
these extreme
and see by the way it's not really i
mean it can result in extremes sensuality and
it can result in extremes sensuality and
self-modification
but in itself it's relatively subtle in
the beginning it's not
like you denying thoughts it's not
exactly extreme
isn't it yet it already partakes in the
way of extreme self modification shares
the same nature
it's rooted in that so all the acts of
self modification that would come
later on in someone's practice of such
kind would be all sharing the same principle
would be all sharing the same principle
in common
denial of there isn't thought i mustn't
have it
and even the buddha was the same
initially when he was trying to find a
way out
and and there's no end to that you can
always get more and you can always do
more and do more
to the point when the buddha said well
what if i were to stop breathing
so in other words i will kill myself and
i will not
so to not have thoughts so to not have
unwholesome states arise
but then he does well actually that's
that's not going to help that's not
going to work
so the reason i'm saying this because
people kind of tend to dismiss oh yeah
self-modification asceticism
or extreme sensuality those are extremes
as long as i don't commit to those
extremes i'm in the middle no if you're
already either
accepting your thoughts or denying them
you're not in the middle
so the middle way is the way that
basically can discern the arisen thought
know that after not and not act out of
it and not try to get rid of it
which means the mind already needs to
have been developed sufficiently to be
able to allow the thought to endure
without jumping into the action on
account of it
so sense restraint needs to be developed
beforehand virtue needs to be
established because they will prevent you they will
because they will prevent you they will
give you a certain space to not just
automatically act out of it
yeah you're not you're not denying those
thoughts no that's
so that's what i mean like kind of it's
a natural progression first you see
sensuality is a problem you want to deal
with it so what you do you deny the
whole thing
but you deny things you shouldn't be
denying and by denying them you're
abated you're hooked to that bait again
and that's the the dear heard similarly
in the imaginakaya
oh look they got caught by engaging in
sensuality what if we stop and we run on
top of a mountain and we don't eat don't
drink but then you can't sustain that you come
but then you can't sustain that you come
back and you're caught again
and then the third one is the one that
finds them the middle way oh how
do what if we don't eat we eat around
the bait we don't need the bait
so we don't do that which baits us into
mara's domain
but we don't we don't shun it either
because that would all equally makes us
visible to the hunter
and that's that's that's the beginning
of that this sermon is
uh being able to allow thoughts to
endure without welcoming them because thoughts
without welcoming them because thoughts
arise on their own that's the whole
point so you thinking you can deny them or it
so you thinking you can deny them or it
implies wrong view
whereby you think you're in charge of
those thoughts you're responsible for
your arising no
you're responsible for their acceptance
you're responsible for delighting in
them you're responsible for acting out of
you're responsible for acting out of
them
so if you don't do these things and
thoughts are still there that's not on
you but the reason why people then still
but the reason why people then still
want to get rid of those thoughts
is because it's unpleasant to allow
thoughts to endure without acting out of
it
it's easier to act towards sensuality
and it's easier to act towards denial
the hardest thing is to allow it to
endure and not act out of it
because you can do for days
and you're not acting out of it and it's
there the whole pressure emotional
charge it's all there but you're not
acting out of it
it's easier to just get angry or get
lustful just say yes or say no or act
just say yes or say no or act
express yourself quickly deal with it
whatever it is it's easier
but again the only reason you're doing
it is because the endurance of the
thought is first
and it's still there which means it
doesn't matter how much you give in try
to deny it
you always do it on account of that
which you're not in control of that
bothers you which is endurance of the
thought in other words it's futile all of your
in other words it's futile all of your
efforts to act
they come out of it as a reaction to it
are futile
if you really want to deal with the
painfulness of enduring thought
when you're not acting out of it well
you need to allow it to endure and then
understand it
see it clearly yeah that's why i said
there is no wisdom arising on a kind of
central behavior and there will be no
wisdom arising on a kind of
that self-modification asceticism
behavior of just saying no to everything
there will be no wisdom
pushing away or denying because you just
lock into a direction
and that's your principle of action if
it rises i just say yes yes yes or
now you go the other way whatever arises
i just say no no
no no no and then you conflate that with
the idea of purity and then you feel
even extra superior on account of your
great determination that you eat once a
month or something
nobody can do that about you you're so
special so you realize even the unwholesome
so you realize even the unwholesome
states that you wanted to abandon the
conceit ego pride i could get amplified and you
ego pride i could get amplified and you
haven't actually abandoned it
so the endurance of the thought whatever
thought whatever the thought is
whatever the state of mind is you have
to allow it to endure
and what that means not act out of it
and don't try to get rid of it doesn't
mean maintaining no no you don't need to keep
maintaining no no you don't need to keep
it in no that's again that's not it's
not up to you
just ask yourself the state of mind you
have now whatever mood you're in
did you create it did you have a spread
did you like press an internal button
that produced it not at all but that's
what that's kind of what you would think
but that's the
kind of feeling yeah that's the
implication that the people the view
behind it's kind of oh this is mine
yeah which is exactly why it's like oh
this is mine so i engage with it
or when you start seeing problem with
that this is my so i will deny it
but the fact is that that's still there
you realize oh i can't even deny this
so the problem is not in this that in in
those mental states or thoughts arising
the problem is in you acting out of it
either towards
or against either way you're affirming
their grip over you
so you're trying to with a lot of it
so that will be the beginning of the
middle way and that's exactly like
what um in the suit is the grasping the
signs of your mind
cheetah what it is like grasping the
for what it is the mind for its nature
the way it has arisen the way it endures
the reason why people cannot grasp the
chitanimata a prerequisite for the right
view is because they either act or deny
is because they either act or deny
against their own mind so the mind of
sensuality they're fully projected to a central
they're fully projected to a central
action already
or the mind of sensuality fully
projected to a denial of the entire mind
of all the the root of the thoughts not
just this specific thing
so you're either underdoing the
restraint or overdoing the restraint but
you're not doing the restraint properly
either way
because you'll be watching your breaths
and you'll be watching your breath
some people you know doing this
meditation
and then a lustful thought comes up no
i must get rid of this i must watch my
breath i must watch my breath so that i don't
i must watch my breath so that i don't
have lustful thoughts and if i just keep
on watching my breath watching my breath
as hard as i can yeah then whatever
eight hours a day
i i don't have any lustful thoughts yeah
because i'm just watching my best yeah
that's like the deer heard that runs on
top of a mountain they're not
experiencing any temptation from debate
for a period of time but they're not
growing wisdom in regard to overcoming the bait
wisdom in regard to overcoming the bait
altogether which means
the food will have to run out in other
words you can't sustain meditating
breathing eight hours a day watching
something will have to pull you one way
or the other
you'll get sick you have to deal with
things and then you're back to where you
before there's no wisdom there
creating like elevated ground for you to
be on in regard to all these things they
were pulling your
thought
environment that was helping you not
engage with debate
is gone so in other words your freedom
from lustful thoughts was only circumstantial
lustful thoughts was only circumstantial
and our circumstances have changed and
you're back to it
and by the way there is no problem if if
if you want
if you have lustful thoughts while
you're breathing and you choose to
attend to the breath you can do that
because it is a method of choice
will i choose to attend this or just
attend that but the problem is when
people choose to attend breath
like with the view of denying the
thought not like
i will attend my breath and allow this
thought to endure in the background of
my mind because it has arisen on its own
i didn't invite it
i will allow it to do it as long as you
want i will not give my attention to it
i will attend to my breath
but not i will attend to my breath so
this thought is gone i do away with it
it doesn't exist
no now you ah so you're actually engaged
with it then your breath is actually
secondary because this is now your concern that
because this is now your concern that
thought
and that's like when the mara comes in
the suit and tries to tempt
the buddha can't chase him away he can't
kick him and tell him
you know get lost he can just not
provide him a basis to
to latch on and then mara leaves you on
his own so literally thoughts of
sensuality come
and like like flies fly around you but
they have nothing to land on
unless you provide something suitable
for them to land on
so when when even in the system says you
don't you don't pay attention to these
thoughts you don't do it at the expense
of denying their presence
it's it's because they're present you
don't give them your attention
i wouldn't have to not give you my
attention if you're not here
if i'm instructed to not give you my
attention means i know you are here
and for the duration of that endurance
of your presence here
i will not give you my attention but not
i will not give you my attention i will
not give my attention i hope he
disappears now that's wishful thinking now and
now that's wishful thinking now and
you're actually still denying
the presence of that thing that you had
nothing to do with and that's how mara
gets you
that's still his domain affirming or
denying it's his domain
so that's been economist well there will
be the outcome of that
if you cultivate this long enough mara
will leave you alone the pressure will
not be able to overwhelm your mind
but not if you cultivate um sense
restraint in itself
that's necessary basis for you to see
the middle way
for you to stop denying trying to deny
thoughts and states of mind
but allow them to endure and then
basically you become
stronger than those states of mind so to
speak
through having them endure and not
acting out of it not losing your sense
restraint and not trying to deny it so you're
and not trying to deny it so you're
cultivating the middleweight
and then yes you will become economist
imperturbable because that's what you've
been cultivating
but those states will dissipate so to
speak there will
be less pressure yes but that's that's
like a
that's a that's a side effect so to
speak that's a that's a
your concern is do you not be moved by
those states even if they last forever
that's the attitude that you should have
not like i will deny
these states forever after or i will
indulge in these states forever after
i would be immovable in regard to these
states as they would have said be like
water be like fire be like
uh be like earth and wind it doesn't get
affected by things that sort of
come through
and you don't practice like i mean if
you want to make that an actual
factual practice yeah you that's done so
on the level of the mental states what
mood am i in
how is that mood affecting my action am
i lashing out am i binge eating am i
seeking centrality
am i irritable am i am i expressing it
am i being
perturbed by these states of mind means
i don't see the mind for what it is i
don't see its nature for what it is
i am not grasping the sign of the mind
correctly the mind of a phenomenon
basically sign of the mind is a sign oh there is
sign of the mind is a sign oh there is
an enduring state of mind
i didn't invite it but i'm certainly not
delighting in it or accepting it
seeing it for what it is and enduring
phenomena and you start seeing that that's it
and you start seeing that that's it
you're already understanding mine to a
greater degree
but if i start doing this with the idea
that oh yeah so that what
oh yeah so that what
watching my mind so that i can get rid
of well you will inevitably start doing
it in a wrong way as well
but that's why the reading the suit is
the no yeah you have to start somewhere
and then don't take your start at face
value take it with a pinch of salt so to speak
take it with a pinch of salt so to speak
so whatever you're doing even if it
makes sense
okay let's see let's test this in a
sense let's let's reflect even more
let's see how unperturbed i am when
these things arise and so on or if i
think certain thoughts
and then you'll see but yeah you will
have to start somehow
and when when you do start
you're going to be starting pretty much
like on your own terms
as i often say which is a wrong way to
start but you have no other way than
that so you have to start somehow but if you
so you have to start somehow but if you
recognize that wait
it's not me contemplating this mind
seeing oh my mind is like this and then
i'm i'm sticking to observation of it
it's more like just finding the state of
mind that's already there
and that's already effortless that's
already proposed
so i'm mindful of my mind i am depressed
i'm elated
i'm my mind lustful my mind is angry no
you start like that but you want to
remove yourself from that equation are
you doing this
observation because why are you why
are you even able to oh my mind is
lustful my mind is angry
why are you able to do that because the
mind is already that
you find it there already enduring as
such so seeing
also whether i'm doing this or not
doesn't matter what really matters is
just not lose that peripheral
sight of the state of mind that's
enduring whether i look at it or not
look at it
or try to outrun it or delight in it ah
it defines my whole experience as a
whole my whole behavior
so you want to see it on that peripheral
level not on the level of i'm attending
to my mind which is kind of impossible
so if you've got a peaceful state of
mind this is the piece
same don't be negligent about it
regardless don't don't don't lose it
don't distract yourself from it don't
ignore it
oh yeah okay now it's peaceful have i
created that peace
did i create that state of mind do you
know where it came from do you know when
it's gonna know
i'm subjected to it it's agreeable now
okay so let me then not
delight in agreeability of the state of
mind because when that agreeability changes i
because when that agreeability changes i
will not be affected by it
so then equally when the state of mind
that induces disagreeable
you're not delighting in it which means
it's not affecting you as much which
means you don't need to be
fretting over and i must get rid of this
summer's deal with this because it's not
affecting you
because that was the only problem the
problem wasn't there the state of mind
arose one way or the other the problem is that
one way or the other the problem is that
you were affected by it and you were
resisting it
so not being affected by whatever state
tonight not being effective and then seeing that
not being effective and then seeing that
the state of mind are discerned on a
peripheral level not on the level of
your attention i'm looking at my state
of mind
mind is on the level of sense organs not
sense objects
and what people attend is sense objects
i am attending to sight sound smell
taste touch thoughts
but the state of mind is what's
peripheral to that
if you have angry thoughts means you
can't have angry thoughts if the mind is
not angry
so you recognize okay i have angry
thoughts which means the state of mind
that endures
is a state of anger which is going to
feel ambiguous initially because people
want to have things clear-cut where they
can attend to
which is the result of an untrained mind
but training the mind to the sight of
the peripheral image of the mind
is what developing chit animate is
seeing the mind for what it is
without over attending it without under
attending it and forgetting about it
if you cannot see that then you cannot
endure it
exactly exactly not seeing that means
you're already not enduring means you
are either resisting it or in that
or overly welcoming so you can't endure
those thoughts you can't enjoy the mind
if you can't see them
and if you have a view that you
shouldn't be enduring it you will never
see it
as in if you have a view that you should
be denying those thoughts
that represent the state of mind behind
them you will not be
uh able to even endure it because your
view is to not endure it i must get rid
of this
or if habitually you just have a state
of mind that you immediately just act
out of
again you're not enduring it you're
doing it because you can't endure it
so yes the first and foremost even if
you cannot attend
properly in that peripheral manner to
your state of mind
the only way you would be able to do so
if you start enduring
whatever emotional mood you're in know
that out of it not try to get rid of it
but potentiality is bad yes it's very
bad so you don't act out of it you don't
welcome it you don't delight in it
that doesn't mean you go out and try to
remove these thoughts that are there
because that's impossible that means
you're engaging with it
you want to basically be immovable in
regard to that which moves you
not get out and remove that which moves
you that's impossible because how can you go
that's impossible because how can you go
out
and move that which moves you without
being moved without moving yourself
you can't so i want to be movable by
removing making effort to remove that which moves
making effort to remove that which moves
me
well then you're not immovable because
you've been moving because you have to
go and
move it and move this away yeah which
you're trying to get rid of so the only
way to become immovable
imperturbable as the world would say in
the sutures is to then
stop interfering with that which
perturbs you and actually stop being
perturbed by it
while it's there
to perturb it by acting out of it you
perturb it by trying to get rid of it
so when the buddha said to angular he
says stop running
stop running no he said it to the buddha
stop running yeah he said
and yes i stopped i stopped moving yeah
yeah you you won this one yeah
yeah you're the one that still moves
so allowing thoughts state of mind to
endure if they are pleasant endurance will be
if they are pleasant endurance will be
manifested by you not acting towards
that pleasure
if they are unpleasant the endurance
will be manifested by you not
acting or trying to get rid of that
displeasure
and you see sense restraint is already
developing that principle that's why
you start acting beforehand being sense
restrained and virtuous
and then you actually get to understand
the principle behind it
which result results by understanding of
it will result in immovability
but that would have not been possible if
there was no behavior of sense restraint
being performed beforehand wilderness
running around
yeah and that's that's what middleweight
is
the immovable yeah the complete
immovability the face of any phenomenal state of mind
the face of any phenomenal state of mind
that arises
and you can't ask for more you don't
need more
you